Inventory of the Arthur Kemp papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Arthur Kemp papers
1918-1959
62017
Hoover Institution Archives
58 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box (25.1 linear feet)
Correspondence, writings, memoranda, notes, typed copies of documents, and printed matter, relating to Herbert Hoover, American foreign policy and domestic policies during and after the presidential administration of Franklin D. Roosevelt, World War II, international relief and reconstruction, and communism. Used as research material for writing projects of Herbert Hoover. Includes draft writings by Hoover.
Kemp, Arthur, 1916-2002.
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1962.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1916 Born, Buffalo, New York
1939 B.S., University of Buffalo
1940 M.B.A., Northwestern University
1943-1953 Editorial and research assistant to Herbert Hoover
1949 Ph.D., New York University
1953-1981 Professor of economics, Claremont Men's College
1956 Author, The Legal Qualities of Money
1956 Author, The Role of Government in Developing Peaceful Uses of Atomic Energy
1963 Author, The Role of Gold
2002 Died, Claremont, California
Scope and Content of Collection
The Arthur Kemp Papers in the Archives of the Hoover Institution on War, Revolution and Peace are intimately connected with the Institution's Herbert Hoover Papers. The connection is so close that there is an element of the arbitrary as to whether Hoover or Kemp had custody of some items at the time of their deposit. The Kemp Papers are entirely concerned with Kemp's association with Herbert Hoover and do not include materials relating to his subsequent independent career as an economist and educator.
In an oral history interview conducted in 1968, a copy of which is in the Herbert Hoover Oral History Program Collection in the Hoover Institution Archives, Kemp described his association with Hoover. It began in 1943 when, as a graduate student and young economics instructor, he was recruited to go to work for the former President as an editorial and research assistant. Kemp remained in this capacity until 1953 when he left New York to accept a teaching post. He continued to assist Hoover on an occasional basis thereafter.
While Kemp was involved with a variety of Hoover's writing projects, the one that figured most prominently was the so-called Magnum Opus. This was the ambitious critique of the domestic and World War II foreign policy record of Franklin D. Roosevelt that occupied Hoover for decades. It was first known to Hoover and associates simply as the War Book and later as "Lost Statesmanship." The foreign policy component saw published form only in 2011 as Freedom Betrayed: Herbert Hoover's Secret History of the Second World War and Its Aftermath, edited and with an introduction by George H. Nash (Stanford: Hoover Institution Press). While most of the preliminary drafts for this work are in the Herbert Hoover Papers, there are also some in the Herbert Hoover Speeches and Writings series of the Kemp Papers. These include the very first drafts of the War Book, dating back to 1942 and including Hoover's analysis of the Pacific War as a race war. There are also significant procedural memoranda laid out by Hoover for the 1946 version of the War Book, explicitly stating the themes of the project. Small portions of the domestic policy critique, variously entitled "The Years as Crusader" and "Collectivism Comes to America," are also located in this series. Publication of this work is scheduled.
A small Arthur Kemp Speeches and Writings series consists of formal compositions by Kemp, mainly intended for publication under his own name. The most substantial item in the series is a lengthy study of the United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration. There is one oddity in this series. While Kemp's function was normally one of support to Hoover's writing endeavors, a reversal of roles is evident in three letters to the editor written by Kemp under his own name. Their drafts bear editorial suggestions in Hoover's distinctive handwriting, which was quite different from that of Kemp.
The collection includes several subject files, consisting of material other than formal writings by either Hoover or Kemp. This material includes correspondence, notes, many memoranda exchanged between Kemp and Hoover (mainly written by Kemp to apprise Hoover of his research findings and suggestions), and collected items of various descriptions, published and unpublished.
The Herbert Hoover Subject File consists of public commentary about Hoover by third parties, with associated material. Most of this commentary is by critics of Hoover and in a number of cases involved what Hoover regarded as slanderous allegations or "smears." The series includes material gathered by Hoover and Kemp to refute such allegations. There is in particular a sizable volume of material related to charges of anti-Bolshevik manipulative activities by the American Relief Administration in Russia. Some items in this series go back to Hoover's White House days and include Federal Bureau of Investigation reports to President Hoover regarding detractors.
The New Deal Subject File, the Communist Subversion Subject File, and the extensive World War II Subject File are all directly connected to the Magnum Opus and consist of research material on those three topics collected for use in its composition. Of particular interest in the World War II Subject File is material related to Hoover's unsuccessful efforts to initiate wartime food relief to occupied Europe. A large body of other material in this series relates to the wartime American domestic economy and to Hoover's analysis of price controls and of what he regarded as economic policy mismanagement.
The General Subject File includes correspondence, notes, memoranda and collected material not directly used in the Magnum Opus as ultimately composed. In Hoover's mind the Magnum Opus was something of an open-ended project, and the material in this series, as well as that in the corresponding series of the Herbert Hoover Papers, gives some indication of directions in which it might have continued. The great bulk of material in the series deals with the post-World War II period. There is a large volume on the European Recovery Program (Marshall Plan), reflecting Hoover's nuanced views on the potentialities and limitations of American foreign aid. Other material deals more generally with postwar American foreign policy and military policy, again reflecting Hoover's reservations regarding paths taken. Considerable material was collected on the United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration, treatment of which was developed only in Kemp's preliminary study.
There is a significant body of material on Zionism and Palestine. Hoover took an active interest in the plight of European Jewry during World War II, and proposed clearing the way for a Jewish homeland by resettlement of Palestinian Arabs in Iraq, the project to be made palatable by an internationally-sponsored reclamation and development program of the Tigris and Euphrates River valleys.
Another section of the General Subject File is concerned with the work of the postwar Commission on Organization of the Executive Branch of the Government chaired by Hoover. Kemp was employed as an assistant to Hoover in this capacity. The residue from this work in the Kemp Papers is substantial but rather miscellaneous.
There are also a small set of Photographs and a small Oversize File.
Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964.; Communism.; International relief.; Reconstruction (1939-1951); United States--Foreign relations--1933-1945.; United States--Foreign relations--1945-1953.; United States--Politics and government--1933-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Diplomatic history.
- Arthur Kemp Speeches and Writings, 1946-1956 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Typescripts and printed copies of writings by Arthur Kemp, with associated material
  - "The Puzzle of Soviet-U.S. Relations: National Paranoia,", 1946 November 15 (Folder 1: 1)
  - "U.N.R.R.A. Study,", 1946 (Folder 1: 2-3)
    Extensive typescript re United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration, evidently drafted by Kemp for Herbert Hoover, but with little apparent input by Hoover
  - Letter to the editor, New York Times, re criticism by Otto Nathan of Herbert Hoover's views on German industry, 1947 April 15 (Folder 1: 4)
    Typescript, draft with holograph suggestions by Hoover, and printed copy of Nathan's comments
  - Letter to the editor, New York Times, re Herbert Hoover's views on Social Security, 1949 May 6 (Folder 1: 5)
    Typescript and New York Times editorial rejection
  - "The Republican 80th Congress and the 'Fair Deal' 81st Congress,", 1949 (Folder 1: 6)
  - "Hoover Foreign Policy: Stand on Sanctions," letter to the editor, Christian Science Monitor, 1951 April 30 (Folder 1: 7)
    Typescript with holograph suggestions by Herbert Hoover, printed copy, background material, and correspondence
  - Letters to the editor, various journals, re Herbert Hoover's address at Warren G. Harding Memorial dedication and Harding administration scandals, 1951 September-1952 March (Folder 1: 8)
    Holograph, typescripts, and background material
  - Review of Winston Churchill, The Second World War, Volume V, Closing the Ring, 1951 December 14 (Folder 1: 9)
    Typescript and letter of submission to The Freeman
  - "Mr. Stassen's Mortarboard,", 1952 January 3 (Folder 1: 10)
    Typescript
  - "The Crime of Crimea," The Freeman, 1952 January 14 (Folder 1: 11)
    Printed copy
  - "Militarism,", 1952 April 21 (Folder 1: 12)
  - "The Non-Partisan Partisans," review of William L. Langer and S. Everett Gleason, The Challenge to Isolation, 1937-1940, circa 1952 (Folder 1: 13)
    Typescript with holograph suggestions by Herbert Hoover
  - Letters to the editor, New York Times and Santa Ana Register (California), re Herbert Hoover's views on public hydroelectric power, 1953 April-May (Folder 1: 14)
    Typescripts with holograph suggestions by Hoover, and printed copy
  - Biographical assessment of Herbert Hoover, 1953 (Folder 1: 15)
  - Speech to Hoover Commission Study Group, 1956 December 3 (Folder 1: 16)
    Typescript, possibly drafted for Herbert Hoover
- Herbert Hoover Speeches and Writings, 1919-1957 (Box 1-7)
  Holographs, typescripts, page proofs, printed copies, and typed transcripts of speeches and writings by Herbert Hoover, with associated material
  - Statements re American Relief Administration operations in Russia, 1919-1925 (Folder 1: 17)
    Typed transcripts. Includes statements to the press of 1919 April 25, 1920 June 3, 1921 October 17, 1922 February 12, and 1923 March 8; speeches of 1922 May 15 and 1928 May 18; quotes in journal articles; and cables. See also General Subject File/American Relief Administration
  - Press release re food relief to Europe, 1940 October 7 (Folder 1: 18)
    Holograph drafts and typescript. See also World War II Subject File/Food relief
  - Further Addresses upon the American Road, 1938-1940 (Folder 1: 19)
    Printed excerpts
  - Statements re Lend-Lease operations, 1941 March 5 (Folder 1: 20)
    Typescripts
  - "A Call to American Reason," speech, Chicago, Illinois, 1941 June 29 (Folder 1: 21)
    Printed text
  - Draft statement on freedom of the seas, 1941 September 14 (Folder 1: 22)
  - Testimony before United States Senate Committee on Banking and Currency re price controls, 1941 December 16 (Folder 1: 23)
    Typescript, galleys, notes in preparation for oral questions, and correspondence. See also World War II Subject File/United States/Price controls
  - War Book, 1942 version
    - "Diary" (actually chronology of world events and of activities by Herbert Hoover, prepared subsequently to their occurrence)
      - 1937-1938 (Folder 1: 24)
      - 1939 (Folder 1: 25)
      - 1940 (Folder 2: 1)
      - 1941 (Folder 2: 2)
    - Drafts (Folder 2: 3)
  - "The United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration,", 1943 December 27 (Folder 2: 4)
    Typescript drafted by Arthur Kemp and continued in longhand by Herbert Hoover
  - War Book, 1943 version (Folder 2: 5)
    Draft fragments
  - "Some Additions to the Dumbarton Oaks Proposals,", 1945 March 25 (Folder 2: 6)
  - "The San Francisco Conference and Peace," speech, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 1945 April 17 (Folder 2: 7)
  - "Food for the Liberated Countries," speech, New York City, 1945 May 8 (Folder 2: 8)
  - "On the Palestine Question," New York World-Telegram, 1945 November 19 (Folder 2: 9)
    Reprint in Plain Talk, 1948 March
  - War Book, 1945 version (Folder 2: 10)
    "Roosevelt's Foreign Policies." Drafts
  - War Book, 1946 version (Folder 2: 11)
    Procedural memoranda by Herbert Hoover, and draft fragments
  - "The Limits of American Aid to Foreign Countries," press release, 1947 June 16 (Folder 2: 12)
  - "Tentative Memorandum on Future Relief and Rehabilitation of War-Torn Areas,", 1947 July 3 (Folder 2: 13)
    Typescript with cover letter to Bernard Baruch
  - Memorandum re food conservation, 1947 November 24 (Folder 2: 14)
    Possibly drafted for Herbert Hoover by Arthur Kemp. Drafts
  - Statement re inflation, 1947 December (Folder 2: 15)
    Drafts and galleys
  - War Book, 1947 version (Folder 3: 1)
    Page proofs
  - "The Marshall Plan,", 1948 January 22
    Press release in the form of an open letter to Senator Arthur H. Vandenberg dated 1948 January 18. See also Herbert Hoover Subject File/General/European Recovery Program (Marshall Plan) views
    - Drafts (Folder 3: 2)
    - Galleys (Folder 3: 3-5)
    - Printed copy and memoranda re distribution (Folder 3: 6)
  - "The Marshall Plan Bill,", 1948 March 24 (Folder 3: 7)
    Statement in the form of an open letter to Speaker Joseph W. Martin. Drafts. See also Herbert Hoover Subject File/General/European Recovery Program (Marshall Plan) views
  - War Book, 1949 version (Folder 3: 8)
    Chapter 15. "The Known British and American Relations with Japan in 1939." Drafts
  - War Book, unknown versions
    - Fragments (Folder 3: 9)
    - Appendices (Folder 4: 1)
      Page proofs with corrections
  - "World Peace and the United Nations," speech, Emporia, Kansas, 1950 July 11 (Folder 4: 2)
  - "The Years as Crusader,", 1951 (Folder 4: 3)
    Draft fragment
  - "The Years as Crusader," unknown versions
    - Drafts and assembled documents re presidential election of 1940 (Folder 4: 4-6)
      See also Photographs
    - Drafts and assembled documents re presidential election of 1944 (Folder 4: 7-8)
  - "My White House Years," Collier's, 1952 May 3-10 (Folder 5: 1)
    Serialized memoir excerpts. Printed copies and publisher correspondence
  - "Government Power Must Be Limited," American Agriculturalist, 1952 October 18 (Folder 5: 2)
  - Forty Key Questions about Our Foreign Policy, 1952 (Folder 5: 3)
    Drafts and publisher correspondence
  - "Federal Socialization of Electric Power," speech, Case Institute of Technology, Cleveland, Ohio, 1953 April 11 (Folder 5: 4)
  - "Lost Statesmanship,", 1953 version (Folder 5: 5)
    Editorial memorandum
  - Speech, American Good Government Society dinner, Washington, D.C., 1954 February 22 (Folder 5: 6)
  - "The Editors and the Federal Deficit," speech to American Society of Newspaper Editors, Washington, D.C., 1954 April 17 (Folder 5: 7)
  - "Some Hope for Peace," speech, Bonn, Germany, 1954 November 24 (Folder 5: 8)
  - "Resistance to Communism," speech, Berlin, Germany, 1954 November 26 (Folder 5: 9)
  - "Lost Statesmanship,", 1954
    - Procedural memoranda and notes (Folder 5: 10)
    - Drafts and page proofs with corrections
      - Part I. "Isolationism, 1932-1938" (Folder 5: 11)
      - Part II. "The Rising World Explosion in 1938-1939" (Folder 5: 12)
      - Part III. "Munich (September 1938) to the Outbreak of War (September 1939)" (Folder 5: 13)
      - Part IV. "Outbreak of the War to the Fall of France, 1939-1940" (Folder 5: 14)
      - Part V. "Defeat of France to the Presidential Election, 1940" (Folder 5: 15)
      - Part VI. "From Election 1940 to Alliance with Stalin 1941, November 1940 to July 1941" (Folder 5: 16)
      - Part VII. "From Hitler's Attack on Stalin to Pearl Harbor, 1941" (Folder 5: 17)
      - Part VIII. "The Development of War with Japan" (Folder 6: 1)
      - Part IX. "Pearl Harbor to Yalta, 1941-1945" (Folder 6: 2)
      - Part X. "From Yalta to the Japanese Surrender, February to August 1945" (Folder 6: 3)
      - Part XI. "The Consequences of War" (Folder 6: 4)
  - "Lost Statesmanship," unknown versions
    - Draft fragments (Folder 6: 5)
    - Page proofs (Folder 7: 1)
  - "The Work of the Commission on Reorganization of the Government," radio address, 1955 May 19 (Folder 7: 2)
  - "Government Is Too Big," interview transcript, U.S. News and World Report, 1955 August 5 (Folder 7: 3)
  - "Inflation, Spending, Taxes and Some Reforms," speech, Washington, D.C., 1957 February 4 (Folder 7: 4)
  - "Collectivism Comes to America,", undated (Folder 7: 5)
    Detailed table of contents for Volume II, "Roosevelt's Second Term, 1936-40"
- Herbert Hoover Subject File, 1922-1952 (Box 7-11)
  Published and unpublished comments about Herbert Hoover, and correspondence, memoranda, and printed matter about them. Consists mainly, but not exclusively, of material regarding criticisms of Hoover, and characterized by him as "smears." Arranged by name of commentator
  - General
    - General. Letters, clippings, and biographical and bibliographical data, 1939-1954 (Folder 7: 6)
    - Assassination threats. Letters and memoranda, 1931-1932 (Folder 7: 7)
    - Bonus March, 1932 (Folder 7: 8)
      Letter and printed article
    - Business enterprises. Letters, memoranda, and printed matter, 1928-1952 (Folder 7: 9)
    - Church attendance. Letters, 1931 (Folder 7: 10)
    - European Recovery Program (Marshall Plan) views
      - Correspondence in response to Herbert Hoover Speeches and Writings/"The Marshall Plan,", 1948 January 22 (Folder 7: 11)
      - Clippings in response to Herbert Hoover Speeches and Writings/"The Marshall Plan,", 1948 January 22 (Folder 7: 12-13)
      - Clippings in response to Herbert Hoover Speeches and Writings/"The Marshall Plan" (contd.), 1948 January 22 (Folder 8: 1)
      - Clippings in response to Herbert Hoover Speeches and Writings/"The Marshall Plan Bill,", 1948 March 24 (Folder 8: 2)
    - Family. Letters and printed articles, 1928-1931 (Folder 8: 3)
    - Food relief (World War I). Letters, memorandum, and printed article, 1932-1947 (Folder 8: 4)
    - Food relief (World War II). Letters, printed matter, and circulated documents, 1939-1941 (Folder 8: 5)
      See also World War II Subject File/Food relief
    - Foreign policy views. Letters, clippings, and radio broadcast transcripts, reacting to Herbert Hoover's foreign policy radio broadcast of 1950 December 20, 1950-1951 (Folder 8: 6)
    - Harding (Warren G.) administration scandals. Letters, speeches, memoranda, and clippings, reacting to Herbert Hoover's Harding Memorial dedication address of 1951 June 16, 1951-1952 (Folder 8: 7)
    - Oil industry connections. Letters and memoranda, 1930-1932 (Folder 8: 8)
    - P. N. Gray and Company connection (re Czechoslovak government commission). Letters and Federal Trade Commission minutes excerpt, 1922-1928 (Folder 8: 9)
    - Presidency. Letters, memoranda, clippings, and flyers, mainly re criticisms of Herbert Hoover administration, 1931-1952 (Folder 9: 1)
      Includes J. Edgar Hoover reports of investigation of authorship of critical flyers
    - Prohibition. Letters and clippings, 1930-1932 (Folder 9: 2)
    - South American trip, 1928 (Folder 9: 3)
  - Ambruster, Howard Watson, Treason's Peace. Letter, memoranda, and clippings, 1947 (Folder 9: 4)
  - Atchison, Theodore C., Herbert Hoover and Chang Yen Mao: The History of a Trust. Letters and advertising leaflet, 1936 (Folder 9: 5)
  - Baker, Lorin L., That Imperiled Freedom: A Drama of American Politics. Letter, memoranda, and advertising leaflet, 1932 (Folder 9: 6)
  - Cheradame, André. Letter, 1943 (Folder 9: 7)
  - Committee for the Marshall Plan. Press release by the Committee and exchange of letters between Robert P. Patterson (Committee chairman) and Herbert Hoover, 1948 (Folder 9: 8)
  - Communist Party issuances. Printed articles and flyer, 1939-1952 (Folder 9: 9)
  - Corey, Herbert, The Truth about Hoover. Letters, memoranda, and clipping, 1932-1933 (Folder 9: 10)
  - Democratic Party issuances. Letters, memoranda, and printed articles and brochures, 1929-1951 (Folder 9: 11)
  - Dewey, John. Photocopy and transcript of letter by Dewey, 1940 (Folder 9: 12)
  - Hacker, Louis M. Letters and memorandum, 1952 (Folder 9: 13)
  - Haldeman-Julius, E., Herbert Hoover's Record before He Became President. Pamphlet and advertising literature, 1931-1944 (Folder 9: 14)
  - Hamill, John, The Strange Career of Mr. Hoover. Letters, memoranda, printed articles, and transcript of legal deposition by Hamill, 1931-1933 (Folder 9: 15)
  - Hart, Hornell. Letters and transcript of printed article by Hart, 1951 (Folder 9: 16)
  - Hinshaw, David, Herbert Hoover: American Quaker. Letters, memoranda, and clipping, 1949-1950 (Folder 9: 17)
  - Kauffman, Reginald Wright. Printed article and memorandum re origin of "chicken in every pot" phrase, 1951 (Folder 9: 18)
  - Liggett, Walter W. Printed notice, 1952 (Folder 9: 19)
  - Livingstone, Belle. Correspondence, memoranda, printed article by Livingstone alleging acquaintance with Herbert Hoover, and photocopies of legal depositions, 1925-1927 (Folder 10: 1)
  - Moley, Raymond. Letters, notes, clippings, and printed articles by Moley, 1939-1949 (Folder 10: 2)
  - Myers, William Starr, The True Republican Record, 1929-1933, printed copy, 1939 (Folder 10: 3)
  - Orr, Hugh Robert. Letter and printed article, 1931-1946 (Folder 10: 4)
  - Pearson, Drew. Letters, press releases, memoranda, and clippings, 1939-1947 (Folder 10: 5)
  - Roach, Daniel T. Letters and memoranda, 1951 (Folder 10: 6)
  - Sayers, Michael, and Albert E. Kahn, The Great Conspiracy against Russia
    - Printed copy of Boni and Gaer edition, 1946 (Folder 10: 7)
    - Correspondence, 1946 (Folder 10: 8)
    - Background material assembled to refute allegations in book, mainly typed transcripts from American Relief Administration records (Folder 10: 9)
    - Background material assembled to refute allegations in book (contd.) (Folder 11: 1)
  - Schlesinger, Arthur, Jr. Letters, memoranda, notes, and printed copies of letters to the editor by Schlesinger and in reaction to his comments, 1950-1952 (Folder 11: 2)
  - Scofield, Lou. Letters, and transcript of radio broadcast by Scofield, 1945 (Folder 11: 3)
  - Seldes, George. Letter, and printed copies and typed transcripts of articles from In Fact, journal edited by Seldes, 1943-1945 (Folder 11: 4)
  - Sergio, Lisa. Letter, memoranda, and transcript of radio broadcast by Sergio, 1943 (Folder 11: 5)
  - Stout, Rex. Letters, memoranda, transcripts, and printed matter, 1941-1945 (Folder 11: 6)
  - United States. Senate. Special Committee on Investigation of the Munitions Industry (Nye Committee). Letters, statements, memoranda, and clippings, 1925-1934 (Folder 11: 7)
  - Wagner, Gustave H. Letters and printed matter, 1930-1931 (Folder 11: 8)
  - Wells, H. G. Printed excerpt and transcript from books, 1932 (Folder 11: 9)
  - Winn, H. Oscar, and S. Q. Sevier. Letters and legal brief, 1929-1933 (Folder 11: 10)